News for Alumni/AE, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine UP035
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
News for Alumni/AE, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine
1985 -- 2006
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine
UP035
0.25 Linear Feet
107.9 Megabytes 30 PDFs
This collection contains issues of Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine's publication News for Alumni/ae.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized chronologically in five series: News for Alumni/AE, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine; News for Alumni and Alumnae, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine; Alumni/ae News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine; Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine; and Tufts Veterinary Alumni News.
Biographical / Historical
The School of Veterinary Medicine was established in 1978, opened in 1979, and graduated its first class in 1983. Established through the advocacy of President Jean Mayer, the school was unique in its affiliation to a health sciences complex rather than to a school of agriculture. The school is located on a 634 acre campus in Grafton, Massachusetts, site of a former state mental hospital. The school also shares facilities with the medical and dental schools on the downtown Boston campus, where vet students receive their first year of instruction in the basic sciences. Students at the veterinary school are exposed to care of all types of animals including food (cattle, sheep, swine, goat), fiber (sheep, llama), companion (dog, cat), and sporting (horse) animals. In addition, students are given the option of learning about care for wildlife through the wildlife medicine program. In addition to medicine, surgery, preventive medicine, and public health, the school also educates students about ethics, conservation medicine, and human-animal relationships.
Initial discussions on the establishment of a veterinary school were begun in the early 1970s as the absence of such a school in the New England region combined with a prediction of a nationwide deficit of veterinarians made the need apparent. After a variety of options were explored, including locating a school at the Otis Air Force base on Cape Cod, Tufts, under Jean Mayer's leadership, stepped forward to take the lead in the project. Richard B. Talbot, dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University was brought in as interim dean to oversee the startup of the school on a part-time basis. On April 29, 1978, the trustees voted to establish the school as part of Mayer's vision of an integrated "one medicine" program embracing the totality of medical, dental, veterinary, and nutrition education.
The school provides clinical facilities as part of the Tufts-New England Veterinary Medical Center, which includes the Foster Hospital for Small Animals, the Large Animal Hospital, the Cornelius Thibeault Equine Clinic, the Amelia Peabody Pavilion, the Issam Fares Equine Sports Medicine Program, the Harrington Oncology Program, and the Wildlife Clinic at Grafton, as well as the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole, and the Ambulatory Farm Clinic based at Woodstock, Connecticut.
The degree of Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (D.V.M.) is the primary degree offered by the school, though since 1995 the school also offers a Master of Science (M.S.) in Animals and Public Policy. The school features several signature programs which offer specialized perspectives on veterinary sciences, including Wildlife Medicine, Equine Sports Medicine, International Veterinary Medicine, Ethics and Values in Veterinary Medicine, and Biotechnology and Veterinary Medicine.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains five print issues between 1985 and 1988 as well as digitized copies of the publication. It covers news for and about alumni of the Veterinary School. It was originally published twice a year, but the frequency and timing of publication varied beginning in the mid-1990s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Digitized copies of News for Alumni/ae were transferred by the Webster Family Library, 2019, accession UA-2020-014.
- News for Alumni/AE, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1985 -- 1988; UP035.001; 0.25 Linear Feet; 13 Megabytes 5 PDFs
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains five issues between 1985 and 1988. It covers news for and about alumni of the Veterinary School. It was published twice a year.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Alumni/AE News Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1985-08; UP035.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Alumni/AE News Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Spring, 1986; UP035.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Alumni/AE News Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1986-12; UP035.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - News for Alumni and Alumnae Tufts School of Veterinary Medicine, 1987-07; UP035.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - News for Alumni and Alumnae Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1988-10; UP035.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
- News for Alumni and Alumnae, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1991 -- 1994; UP035.000008; 5.93 Megabytes 4 PDFs
  This series contains digitized copies of News for Alumni and Alumnae, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine.
  - News for Alumni and Alumnae, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1991 December; UP035.000009; 1 Megabytes
  - News for Alumni and Alumnae, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1992 July; UP035.000010; 925 Kilobytes
  - News for Alumni and Alumnae, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1993; UP035.000011; 2 Megabytes
  - News for Alumni and Alumnae, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1994; UP035.000012; 2 Megabytes
- Alumni/ae News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1995 -- 1998; UP035.000013; 4 Megabytes 2 PDFs
  This series contains digitized copies of Alumni/ae News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine.
  - Alumni/ae News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Spring 1995; UP035.000014; 2 Megabytes
  - Alumni/ae News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Summer 1995; UP035.000015; 2 Megabytes
- Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, 1996 -- 1998; UP035.000016; 19 Megabytes 6 PDFs
  This series contains digitized copies of Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine.
  - Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Spring 1996; UP035.000017; 3 Megabytes
  - Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Summer 1996; UP035.000018; 2 Megabytes
  - Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Winter 1996; UP035.000019; 2 Megabytes
  - Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Spring 1997; UP035.000020; 3 Megabytes
  - Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Summer 1998; UP035.000021; 5 Megabytes
  - Alumni News, Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, Winter 1998; UP035.000022; 4 Megabytes
- Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, 2000 -- 2006; UP035.000023; 43 Megabytes 13 PDFs
  This series contains digitized copies of Tufts Veterinary Alumni News.
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Spring 2000; UP035.000025; 3 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Fall 2000; UP035.000024; 6 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Spring 2001; UP035.000027; 2 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Fall 2001; UP035.000026; 4 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Winter 2002; UP035.000029; 2 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Summer -- Fall 2002; UP035.000028; 3 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Winter -- Spring 2003; UP035.000031; 2 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Summer -- Fall 2003; UP035.000030; 4 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Winter -- Spring 2004; UP035.000032; 3 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Fall -- Winter 2004 -- 2005; UP035.000033; 4 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Spring -- Summer 2005; UP035.000034; 4 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Winter 2006; UP035.000036; 3 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary Alumni News, Summer 2006; UP035.000035; 3 Megabytes